
[
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is NOT a typical characteristic of Bacillus anthracis?",
      "choices": [
        "Gram-positive rod",
        "Spore-forming",
        "Susceptible to cephalosporins",
        "Causes a predominantly animal disease"
      ],
      "answer": "Susceptible to cephalosporins",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
      {
      "question": "Which of the following is the most common type of anthrax infection in humans?",
      "choices": [
        "Gastrointestinal",
        "Cutaneous",
        "Inhalational",
        "Meningeal"
      ],
      "answer": "Cutaneous",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the primary mechanism of pathogenesis in tetanus?",
      "choices": [
        "Direct bacterial invasion of tissues",
        "Inhibition of inhibitory neurotransmission",
        "Activation of stimulatory neurotransmission",
        "Spore formation in healthy tissues"
      ],
      "answer": "Inhibition of inhibitory neurotransmission",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which cranial nerve is most commonly affected in cephalic tetanus?",
      "choices": [
        "CN III",
        "CN IV",
        "CN VII",
        "CN XII"
      ],
      "answer": "CN VII",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
        "question":"Which clostridial species is correctly matched with disease it commonly causes",
        "choices":[
          "Clostridum difficile - tetanus",
          "Clostridum tetani - botulism ",
          "Clostridum perferingens - gas gangrene ",
          "Clostridum botulinum - antibiotic associated colitis "
  ],
      "answer":"Clostridum perferingens - gas gangrene",
      "topic":"Infectious Diseases"
    },
   {
      "question": "Which of the following antibiotics is LEAST likely to be associated with Clostridium difficile infection?",
      "choices": [
        "Clindamycin",
        "Penicillins",
        "Cephalosporins",
        "Vancomycin"
      ],
      "answer": "Vancomycin",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the most reliable diagnostic test for C. difficile infection?",
      "choices": [
        "Stool culture",
        "Stool test for C. difficile toxin and toxin B gene",
        "Lower GI endoscopy",
        "PCR"
      ],
      "answer": "Stool test for C. difficile toxin and toxin B gene",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which of the following is a virulence factor of Bacillus anthracis?",
      "choices": [
        "Tetanospasmin",
        "Protective antigen",
        "Botulinum toxin",
        "Enterotoxin A"
      ],
      "answer": "Protective antigen",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is NOT a typical manifestation of cutaneous anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Painless papule",
        "Black eschar",
        "Extensive edema",
        "Painful, purulent ulcer"
      ],
      "answer": "Painful, purulent ulcer",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
      {
      "question": "What is the recommended treatment for systemic anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Antibiotic monotherapy",
        "Antimicrobial combination therapy",
        "Cephalosporins alone",
        "Supportive care only"
      ],
      "answer": "Antimicrobial combination therapy",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
   {
        "question": "What is the most frequent means of transmission of C. tetani in neonatal tetanus?",
        "choices":[
          "Ingestion of contaminated food",
          "Unclean management of the umbilical stump",
          "Penetrating injuries",
          "Inhalation of spores"
          ],
          "answer":"Unclean management of the umbilical stump",
        "topic":"Infectious Diseases"
      },
        {
        "question": "Which of the following clinical situations is NOT typically associated with an increased risk of tetanus?",
        "choices":[
          "Septic abortion",
          "Dental infections",
          "Infected umbilical stump in neonates",
          "Unimmunized mothers"
        ],
          "answer":"Dental infections",
      "topic":"Infectious Diseases"
      },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the MOST appropriate initial treatment for a patient with severe tetanus?",
      "choices": [
        "Metronidazole or penicillin G",
        "Human tetanus immunoglobulin (HTIG)",
        "Benzodiazepines",
        "Airway management"
      ],
      "answer": "Airway management",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
      {
      "question": "Which of the following is a key component of tetanus treatment to halt toxin production?",
      "choices": [
        "Antitoxin administration",
        "Wound management",
        "Active immunization",
        "Beta-blocker administration"
      ],
      "answer": "Wound management",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which finding is MOST consistent with a diagnosis of severe tetanus?",
      "choices": [
        "Incubation period > 14 days",
        "Mild trismus",
        "Onset time < 3 days",
        "Localized spasm and rigidity"
      ],
      "answer": "Onset time < 3 days",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which form of tetanus is characterized by symptoms limited to one part of the body and is often less severe?",
      "choices": [
        "Generalized tetanus",
        "Local tetanus",
        "Cephalic tetanus",
        "Neonatal tetanus"
      ],
      "answer": "Local tetanus",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the primary aim of treatment in tetanus?",
      "choices": [
        "Neutralizing unbound toxin",
        "Antagonizing the effects of bound toxin",
        "Halting toxin production",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "All of the above",
      "topic": "Infectious Diseases"
    },
   {
        "question": "What is the primary mechanism by which Clostridium difficile causes diarrhea?",
        "choices":[
          "Direct invasion of the intestinal wall",
          "Disruption of normal intestinal flora",
          "Production of exotoxins",
          "Formation of spores"
            ],
          "answer":"Production of exotoxins",
          "topic":"Infectious Diseases"
      },
    {
      "question": "What is the most common clinical feature of Clostridioides difficile infection (CDI)?",
      "choices": [
        "Asymptomatic infection",
        "Watery diarrhea",
        "Bloody diarrhea",
        "Protein-losing enteropathy"
      ],
      "answer": "Watery diarrhea",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which imaging finding is MOST characteristic of inhalational anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Lung infiltrates",
        "Mediastinal widening",
        "Consolidation",
        "Effusion"
      ],
      "answer": "Mediastinal widening",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the MOST common type of anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Cutaneous",
        "Gastrointestinal",
        "Inhalational",
        "Oropharyngeal"
      ],
      "answer": "Cutaneous",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
      {
      "question": "Which statement BEST describes the progression of cutaneous anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Starts as a vesicle, progresses to a painless papule, then forms a black eschar",
        "Starts as a small painless papule, then a vesicle, and forms a necrotic ulcer with a black eschar",
        "Always presents with extensive edema and regional lymphadenopathy",
        "Forms a painful, necrotic ulcer without a black eschar"
      ],
      "answer": "Starts as a small painless papule, then a vesicle, and forms a necrotic ulcer with a black eschar",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
   {
      "question": "What is the causative agent of anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Clostridium tetani",
        "Bacillus anthracis",
        "Clostridium difficile",
        "Bacillus cereus"
      ],
      "answer": "Bacillus anthracis",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which statement regarding B. anthracis susceptibility is TRUE?",
      "choices": [
        "It is susceptible to cephalosporins.",
        "It is susceptible to cotrimoxazole.",
        "It is susceptible to penicillin.",
        "It is resistant to fluoroquinolones."
      ],
      "answer": "It is susceptible to penicillin.",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which diagnostic test is MOST useful for confirming inhalational anthrax?",
      "choices": [
        "Culture and sensitivity",
        "PCR",
        "Antibody detection during convalescence",
        "Chest X-ray showing mediastinal widening"
      ],
      "answer": "Chest X-ray showing mediastinal widening",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which clinical syndrome is associated with the 'pathology of tissue necrosis surrounded by brawny edema'?",
      "choices": [
        "Gastrointestinal anthrax",
        "Inhalational anthrax",
        "Cutaneous anthrax",
        "Meningeal anthrax"
      ],
      "answer": "Cutaneous anthrax",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the primary aim of antibiotic therapy in streptococcal pharyngitis?",
      "choices": [
        "To shorten the course of the illness",
        "To prevent suppurative complications and ARF",
        "To reduce the severity of symptoms",
        "To prevent transmission to others"
      ],
      "answer": "To prevent suppurative complications and ARF",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a suppurative complication of GAS pharyngitis?",
      "choices": [
        "Acute rheumatic fever",
        "Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis",
        "Peritonsillar abscess",
        "Scarlet fever"
      ],
      "answer": "Peritonsillar abscess",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
      {
      "question": "Which statement BEST describes the rash associated with scarlet fever?",
      "choices": [
        "Limited to the face and neck",
        "Spares the palms and soles",
        "Feels smooth to the touch",
        "Typically resolves within 24 hours"
      ],
      "answer": "Spares the palms and soles",
      "topic": "Respiratory System"
    },
    {
      "question": "What feature is commonly seen in the blood smear of a patient with staphylococcal infection?",
      "choices": [
        "Gram-positive cocci in chains",
        "Gram-positive cocci in grape-like clusters",
        "Gram-negative rods",
        "Gram-positive rods"
      ],
      "answer": "Gram-positive cocci in grape-like clusters",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
   {
      "question": "Which of the following is NOT a typical site of colonization by S. aureus?",
      "choices": [
        "Anterior nares",
        "Oropharynx",
        "Urinary tract",
        "Damaged skin"
      ],
      "answer": "Urinary tract",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which clinical setting is S. aureus MOST likely to cause infective endocarditis?",
      "choices": [
        "Community-acquired pneumonia",
        "Surgical wound infections",
        "IV drug users",
        "Urinary tract infections"
      ],
      "answer": "IV drug users",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the primary mechanism of disease in staphylococcal food poisoning?",
      "choices": [
        "Invasion of the intestinal lining",
        "Toxin-mediated effects",
        "Formation of abscesses",
        "Immune evasion"
      ],
      "answer": "Toxin-mediated effects",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
      {
      "question": "What is a common finding on imaging in vertebral osteomyelitis caused by S. aureus in adults?",
      "choices": [
        "Long bone involvement",
        "Back pain and fever",
        "Normal X-ray for up to 14 days",
        "Blood culture +ve in 50% of cases"
      ],
      "answer": "Back pain and fever",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the characteristic skin lesion associated with Staphylococcal Scalded Skin Syndrome?",
      "choices": [
        "Nikolsky sign positive",
        "Painful, necrotic ulcer with a black eschar",
        "Small, painless papules",
        "Hemorrhagic mediastinitis"
      ],
      "answer": "Nikolsky sign positive",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a key immune evasion strategy employed by staphylococci?",
      "choices": [
        "Production of tetanospasmin",
        "Tendency to form abscesses",
        "Inhibition of inhibitory neurotransmission",
        "Production of weaponized spores"
      ],
      "answer": "Tendency to form abscesses",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which statement BEST describes the role of Coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS) in infections?",
      "choices": [
        "They are more virulent than S. aureus.",
        "They are primarily associated with prosthetic devices.",
        "They are catalase-negative.",
        "They are easily distinguished from S. aureus on Gram stain."
      ],
      "answer": "They are primarily associated with prosthetic devices.",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
      {
      "question": "Which of the following is the MOST common cause of surgical wound infections?",
      "choices": [
        "CoNS",
        "S. aureus",
        "Streptococcus pyogenes",
        "Pseudomonas aeruginosa"
      ],
      "answer": "S. aureus",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
     {
      "question": "What are the three main toxin-mediated diseases caused by S. aureus?",
      "choices": [
        "Folliculitis, furuncle, carbuncle",
        "Food poisoning, TSS, SSSS",
        "Osteomyelitis, septic arthritis, pyomyositis",
        "Bacteremia, sepsis, endocarditis"
      ],
      "answer": "Food poisoning, TSS, SSSS",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the two important species of coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS) and their typical associations?",
      "choices": [
        "S. epidermidis (skin flora) and S. saprophyticus (UTIs)",
        "S. aureus (skin flora) and S. epidermidis (UTIs)",
        "S. saprophyticus (skin flora) and S. lugdunensis (UTIs)",
        "S. lugdunensis (skin flora) and S. aureus (UTIs)"
      ],
      "answer": "S. epidermidis (skin flora) and S. saprophyticus (UTIs)",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement BEST describes how to interpret blood cultures positive for CoNS?",
      "choices": [
        "CoNS always indicates a true bacteremia.",
        "CoNS often contaminate cultures.",
        "Only 10-25% of blood cultures positive for CoNS reflect true bacteremia.",
        "Multiple isolations of the same strain from separate cultures suggest contamination."
      ],
      "answer": "Only 10-25% of blood cultures positive for CoNS reflect true bacteremia.",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which group of streptococci is primarily responsible for streptococcal pharyngitis and skin infections?",
      "choices": [
        "Group A streptococcus (GAS)",
        "Group B streptococcus (GBS)",
        "Viridans streptococci",
        "Enterococci"
      ],
      "answer": "Group A streptococcus (GAS)",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
     {
      "question": "What is the primary aim of antibiotic treatment for GAS pharyngitis?",
      "choices": [
        "To shorten the duration of illness",
        "To prevent suppurative complications and ARF",
        "To immediately relieve symptoms",
        "To eliminate all bacteria from the throat"
      ],
      "answer": "To prevent suppurative complications and ARF",
      "topic": "Cardiovascular System"
    },
    {
      "question": "All of the following statements are true about the function of the erythron EXCEPT",
      "choices":[
          "Erythron production of RBCs is influenced by renal production of EPO",
          "Erythron production of RBCs is influenced by marrow response",
          "Normal marrow response to anemic stress results in RPI<2",
          "Erythron needs substrate supplement for Hb synthesis",
          "Erythropoietin is produced by the kidney in response to reduced O2 tension"
  ],
      "answer":"Normal marrow response to anemic stress results in RPI<2",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "All of the following can cause anemia through marrow damage, EXCEPT",
      "choices":[
        "Inadequate renal stimulation",
        "Infiltrative diseases",
        "Myeloid leukemia",
        "Aplastic anemia"
  ],
      "answer":"Inadequate renal stimulation",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "All are common clinical features of anemia, EXCEPT",
      "choices":[
          "Exertional dyspnea",
          "Fatigue",
          "Headache",
          "Loss of consciousness"
      ],
      "answer":"Loss of consciousness",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which statement is INCORRECT regarding reticulocyte count?",
      "choices":[
        "Reticulocyte count is a key to classify anemia",
        "Reticulocyte count doesn't refelct bone marrow response to anemia",
        "Reticulocyte Production Index(RPI)is an estimate of marrow production",
        "RPI=Corrected reticulocyte count/correction factor"
      ],
      "answer":"Reticulocyte count doesn't refelct bone marrow response to anemia",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
    {
      "question": "All of the following tests are useful in evaluating iron supply and storage, EXCEPT",
      "choices":[
          "Serum iron",
          "TIBC",
          "Percent transferrin saturation",
          "MCV"
        ],
      "answer":"MCV",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "In the anemia of acute or chronic inflammation, which of the following is typically HIGH?",
      "choices":[
        "Serum iron",
        "TIBC",
        "Percent transferrin saturation",
        "Serum ferritin"
      ],
      "answer":"Serum ferritin",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which type of anemia is characterized by an inappropriately low reticulocyte production index, macro- or microcytosis, and abnormal red cell indices?",
      "choices":[
         "Hypoproliferative anemia",
         "Maturation disorder",
        "Hemolytic anemia",
        "Anemia of acute blood loss"
        ],
        "answer":"Maturation disorder",
       "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
     },
     {
      "question": "Which of the following is NOT a typical feature of megaloblastic anemia?",
      "choices":[
          "Vitamin B12 or folic acid deficiency",
          "Hypersegmented neutrophils",
          "Oval macrocytosis",
          "Increased reticulocyte index"
      ],
      "answer":"Increased reticulocyte index",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "In iron deficiency anemia, which of the following lab values is typically HIGH?",
      "choices":[
          "Serum iron",
          "TIBC",
          "Percent transferrin saturation",
          "Serum ferritin"
      ],
      "answer":"TIBC",
      "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
    },
     {
      "question": "Which statement about hemolytic anemia is TRUE?",
      "choices":[
           "It is associated with red cell production indices 2.5 times normal.",
           "A marrow examination is always indicated.",
          "The red cell indices are typically microcytic.",
          "It results from ineffective erythropoiesis."
          ],
          "answer":"It is associated with red cell production indices 2.5 times normal.",
          "topic":"Approach to Anemia"
     }
  ]